Guide to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) Records, 1981-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) records 1981-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Center for Transitional Justice
105 Linear Feet Approximately 59,600 Items
The International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) is a non-profit organization that assists post-conflict, conflict, and democratic countries in pursuing accountability for mass atrocities and human rights abuses.
The International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ) Records include printed materials and publications, country files, staff files, audiovisual materials, a Mena survey, miscellaneous publications, institutional materials, CPU materials, Documentation Center materials, Historical Memory Project and Policymakers Retreat files, and other miscellaneous materials. This accession has not been processed.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
RESTRICTED: Access to the following series is restricted: Accession 2009-0193, Accession 2010-0111, and Accession 2010-0140. Please contact reference archivist for assistance.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The International Center for Transitional Justice Printed Materials were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008-2009.
Collection Overview
The printed material files of the International Center for Transitional Justice span the years 1981 to 2008. Gathered by staff at the ICTJ as a resource file, the files house publications from the United States, Canada, and countries all over the world relating to peace processes and to the pursuit of legal reparations and reconciliation in areas of conflict involving human rights violations. Formats include annual reports, legal journals, human rights organization publications, many types of reports and white papers, conference proceedings, and newspapers, as well as some posters and other ephemera.
The files are arranged in two main series: General Files, which are subdivided into Annual Reports, Conference Files, Journal Issues, Other Printed Material, and Subject Files; and the Geographic Series, arranged into subdivisions for Africa, Asia, Europe, North America, and Latin America, then by individual countries in alphabetical order. There are also separately housed oversize Geographic Series materials, arranged in alphabetical order by country and described at the end of the main collection. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Accession (2009-0193) (76 lin. ft) has not been processed but makes up the majority of the collection's materials. Large components of this accession are African, Asian, European, and South American country files, as well as individual staff files for employees in a variety of ICTJ departments. Also included are audiovisual materials, a Mena survey, ICTJ and miscellaneous publications, institutional materials, CPU materials, Documentation Center materials, Historical Memory Project and Policymakers Retreat files, and other miscellaneous materials. This accession has not been processed, but materials have been described using a folder list below.
Accession (2010-0111) (2.0 lin. ft.) has not been processed. It includes electronic files and drives as well as audiovisual material from the ICTJ Iraq Tribunal. Materials have been described below.
Accession (2010-0140) (2.0 lin. ft.) has not been processed. It includes audiovisual material and electronic drives and discs, along with some handbooks and notes. Materials have been described below.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
Human rights advocacy
Human rights -- Africa
Human rights -- Asia
Human rights -- Europe
Human rights -- Latin America
Human rights -- Periodicals
International Center for Transitional Justice
International courts -- History -- 20th century
International law -- Cases
Peace-building
Reconciliation
Contents of Collection
- General Files Series, 1997-2008, (14 boxes)
  Subdivided into the following subseries further described below: Annual Reports, Conference Files, Journal Issues, Other Printed Material, and Subject Area Files.
  - Annual Reports Subseries, 2000-2008 (Box 1-5)
    Contains reports published chiefly by U.S. non-profit organizations. Broadly speaking, topics concern human rights, economic development, and international law. In addition to the U.S. publications, there are some items originating from countries such as South Africa, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom. Arranged chronologically by year.
  - Conference Files Subseries, 1997-2006 (Box 5-8)
    Contains files from conferences concerning security, human rights, democratic development, reconciliation, and the International Criminal Court. Chronologically ordered by year.
  - Journal Issues Subseries, 2000-2008 (Box 8-10)
    Contains alphabetically organized publications primarily from U.S. sources, including university law reviews. Most include information and opinions on restoring judicial systems and practices in the U.S. and internationally following periods of political and armed conflict.
  - Other Printed Materials Subseries, 2002-2008 (Box 10-11)
    Subdivided into Handbooks and Guides, and Collected Papers, Essays, and Lectures.
    - Handbooks and Guides
      Consists of handbooks, guides, field manuals, and sourcebooks related to human rights, including torture and the death penalty. Also includes materials that serves as guides for procedures and management.
    - Collected Papers/Essays/Lectures
      - Carr Center for Human Rights Policy. Fellows Program, 2004-2005: Working Papers. Cambridge: Harvard University, 2005.
      - Henkin, Alice H., ed. The Legacy of Abuse: Confronting the Past, Facing the Future. New York: The Aspen Institute and New York University School of Law, 2002.
      - Kaufman, Michael, et al. Worldly Conversations: Perspectives from Globetrotters: A Series of Dialogues from the 2002-2003 Season at the Vernon Center. New York: The Lillian Vernon Center for International Affairs at New York University, 2003.
  - Subject Area Files Subseries, 2000-2007, (4 boxes)
    Contains files of multiple topics on human rights and international justice, including genocide, children's and women's rights, refugees, democratic process and elections, truth commissions, international prosecutions, and the International Criminal Court. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
    - Aid
      - Sustainable Development International. 2005 International Aid and Trade Review. London: Sustainable Development International, 2005. (Box 11)
    - Armed Conflict
      - Ballentine, Karen and Heiko Nitzschke. Beyond Greed and Grievance: Policy Lessons from Studies in the Political Economy of Armed Conflict. New York: International Peace Academy, 2003.
    - Children
      - Carpenter, Charli, et al. Protecting Children Born of Sexual Violence and Exploitation in Conflict Zones: Existing Practice and Knowledge Gaps. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public and International Affairs, 2005.
      - Special Representative of the Secretary-General for Children and Armed Conflict. The Impact of Armed Conflict on Children: Filling Knowledge Gaps. New York: United Nations, 2000.
    - Democracy/Elections
      - Reynolds, Andrew. Electoral Systems and the Protection and Presentation of Minorities. London: Minority Rights Group International, 2006.
    - Gender
      Includes reports from UNIFEM, the Open Society Institute and others. Work focuses on women's rights, women in conflict situations, AIDS, and women's opportunities
    - Genocide
      - Schabas, William A. Preventing Genocide and Mass Killing: The Challenge for the United Nations. London: Minority Rights Group International, 2006.
    - Human Rights (General)
      - Carr Center for Human Rights Policy. Measurement and Human Rights: Tracking Progress, Assessing Impact. Cambridge: Harvard University, 2005.
      - Schmid, Brigitte. Continuing the Struggle: Human Rights Defenders in Exile. New York: Forefront, 2005.
      - Solana, Javier. EU Guidelines on Human Rights. Brussels: Council of the European Union, 2005.
      - International Human Rights Law Group. Making Human Rights Real. Washington DC: International Human Rights Law Group.
      - Lindsnæs, Birgit and Thomas Martin, eds. Partners in Progress: Human Rights Reform and Implementation. Copenhagen: The Danish Centre for Human Rights, 2002.
    - International Criminal Court (ICC)
      - International Criminal Court Monitor: The Newspaper of the NGO Coalition for the International Criminal Court, 2001-2005, (8 issues, 2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Insight on the International Criminal Court: Newsletter of the NGO Coalition for the ICC, Issue 7, 2006 Jan.-Feb.
      - ICC Documents
        Contains information packets, assemblies of state parties documents in 2003, and information on coalition members.
      - Office of the Prosecutor, Public Hearings., (1 folder)
      - Works about the ICC., (6 folders)
        Includes opinions on the challenges facing the ICC, progress reports on the implementation of the Rome Statute as well as information related to the Victims and Witnesses Unit.
    - International Human Rights Law
      - Fordham University School of Law. Holocaust Restitution: Reconciling Moral Imperatives with Legal Initiatives and Diplomacy. Fordham University School of Law and the Louis Stein Center for Law and Ethics, 2001.
      - Marino, Catalina Botero and Esteban Restrepo Saldarriaga. Los estándares internacionales y constitucionales de derechos humanos aplicables a los procesos de justicia transicional. Universidad de los Andes.
      - OCHA/IBHI. Project Proposal Relating to Problems of Implementation and Compliance in the field of International Humanitarian and Human Rights Law. OCHA/IBHI, 2001.
      - Morison, John, Kieran McEvoy and Gordon Anthony, eds. Judges, Transition, and Human Rights. Oxford University Press, 2007.
    - Memory
      - Gluck, Carol. Doing Justice to the Past. (Box 13)
    - Post-Conflict/Peace-building/Peacekeeping/Reconciliation
      The section includes publications on a wide range of issues; a considerable portion come from organizations such as the International Peace Academy, the United Nations, and FRIDE.
    - Prosecutions/International Criminal Tribunals (Box 14)
      Contains articles that discuss the development of international criminal trials and the evidence used in those trials. Also contains a report on a working visit of the special court of Sierra Leone as well as a report on torture and state accountability.
    - Refugees/Displaced Persons
      - Brookings-Bern Project on Internal Displacement. Addressing Internal Displacement in Peace Processes, Peace Agreements and Peace-building. Brookings Institute, 2007.
      - Refugee Studies Centre. Forced Migration Review. Refugee Studies Centre, University of Oxford, 2007.
      - Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions. Forced Evictions. Geneva: 2002.
      - Robinson, W. Courtland. Risks and Rights: The Causes, Consequences, and Challenges of Displacement. Washington, DC: The Brookings Institution-SAIS Project on Internal Displacement, 2003.
      - USAID. USAID Assistance to Internally Displaced Persons Policy. Washington, DC: USAID, 2004.
    - Security/Terrorism
      Contains documents that discuss rule of law, the legitimacy of terrorism, the "ticking bomb" scenario, and a report by the United Nations on new challenges and threats to peace.
    - Truth Commissions
      Packets containing pamphlets relating to Peru and South Africa Truth Commissions.
    - United Nations
      - Espósito, Carlos and Jessica Almqvist. Building a New Role for the United Nations: The Responsibility to Protect. Madrid: FRIDE, 2005.
      - Heimann, Fritz and Gillian Dell. Recommendations for Review Mechanism for UN Convention Against Corruption. Berlin: Transparency International, 2007.
- Geographic Series, 1981-2007, (24 boxes)
  Divided into subdivisions for Africa, Asia, Europe, North America, and Latin America. Each geographic area contains newspapers, journal articles and other publications related to governance, rule of law, and political stability. Organized within major divisions with a multi-regional/country section first, followed by country files in alphabetical order. A few publications are in the French language.
  - Africa, 1993-2006, (4.5 boxes)
    - Multi-Country/Regional, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      Contains work on West Africa and also issues related to security, poverty, and war crimes. Materials include journals, workshop reports, and NGO publications.
    - Angola
      - Sogge, David. Angola: La "Buena gobernanza" global tambien es necesaria. Madrid: FRIDE, 2006.
      - Sogge, David. Angola: Global "Good Governance" Also Needed. Madrid: FRIDE, 2006.
    - Burundi
      - Global Rights Magazine. The Long Road Home: Burundi's Land Crisis. Washington, DC: Global Rights, 2005.
    - Chad
      - Republic of Chad. Les crimes et détournements de l'ex-président habré et de ses complices: Rapport de la Commission d'Enquête Nationale du Ministère Tchadien de la Justice. Paris: L'Harmattan, 1993.
    - Congo
      - Bouta, Tsjeard. Assessment of the Ituri Disarmament and Community Reinsertion Program (DCR). The Hague: Netherlands Institute of International Relations, 2005
      - Kabila, Joseph. Attributions et Fonctionnement de la Commission Verite et Reconciliation. 2004
      - International Crisis Group Report. Maintaining Momentum in the Congo: The Ituri Problem. Nairobi; Brussels: International Crisis Group, 2004
    - Côte d'Ivoire
      - International Crisis Group Report. Côte d'Ivoire: No Peace in Sight. Nairobi; Brussels: International Crisis Group, 2004
      - International Crisis Group Report. Côte d'Ivoire: The War is Not Yet Over. Nairobi; Brussels: International Crisis Group, 2003
    - Ghana
      - Ghanian Newspaper Issues
      - Ghana Center for Democratic Development briefing papers, 2001-2002
        Contains four issues
      - Democracy and Development: Quarterly Journal of the Center for Democracy and Development (CDD), Volume 2, Number 5. January-March 2001
      - CDD-Ghana Research Papers, 2000-2005, (6 folders)
        Consists of articles on civil society and the domestic policy environment, civil-military relations, national reconciliation, and human rights.
    - Kenya
      - Constitution of the Kenya Review Commission, 1998-2003 (Box 16)
        Includes a draft bill, news articles, the constitution of the commission, a report on the review, submissions to the National Constitutional Conference, and a summary of proposals.
      - Kenya's Human Rights, 1997-2003
        Includes reports from the Kenya Human Rights Commission.
    - Liberia
      - The Criminal Justice Review, 1999-2000
        Consists of two issues.
      - Other Publications
        Includes reports on security challenges, national reconciliation, community cohesion, and inheritance rights.
      - Liberia War Poster
    - Morocco
      - Hazan, Pierre. Morocco: Betting on a Truth and Reconciliation Commission. Washington, DC: United States Institute of Peace Special Report, 2006
    - Mozambique
      - Christie, Frances and Sam Barnes. Report of the Reintegration of Demobilised Soldiers in Mozambique, 1992-1996. Maputo: UNDP
    - Nigeria
      - Sada, Ibrahim Naiya, Fatima L. Adamu and Ali Ahmad. Promoting Women's Rights through Sharia in Northern Nigeria. Abuja: British Council, 2005 (Box 17)
      - Committee for the Defence of Human Rights Annual Reports, 1995-2000
    - Rwanda
      - Intra-Rwandan Dialogue. Time and Space for the Reconstruction of the Rwandan Socio-Economic Weave. Barcelona: Xarxa Internacional per la Veritata i la Reconciliació a Rwanda, 2006
      - Powley, Elizabeth. Strengthening Governance: The Role of Women in Rwanda's Transition. Washington DC: Hunt Alternatives Fund, 2003
    - Sierra Leone
      - Truth and Reconciliation Commission Materials, 2002-2004, (2 folders)
        Consists of reports by the Commission to the United Nations and a report on conditions for the children of Sierra Leone.
      - Special Court for Sierra Leone Publications, 2003-2005, (1 folder)
        Includes two annual reports by the President of the Special Court for Sierra Leone.
      - Newspaper Issues
      - Other Publications, 2002-2005, (4 folders)
        Contains the first Sierra Leone Law Review issue, as well as publications on work on the Special Court, community-driven development, and peace-building.
    - Somalia
      - International Crisis Group Report. Biting the Somali Bullet. Nairobi; Brussels: International Crisis Group, 2004
    - South Africa
      - Publications, 1999-2006, (8 folders) (Box 18)
        Contains an annual report by the Centre for the Study of Violence and Reconciliation, work on the protection of social rights, and one on the government's reparation policy.
    - Sudan
      - International Crisis Group Report. Darfur Deadline: A New International Action Plan. Washington, DC: International Crisis Group, 2004
      - Srinivasan, Sharath. Minority Rights, Early Warning and Conflict Prevention: Lessons from Darfur. London: Minority Rights International, 2006
    - Uganda
      - The Examiner: A Quarterly Publication of Human Rights Focus, 2005
      - Other Publications, 2004-2006
        Includes reports on the Lord's Resistance Army and the ICC, peace negotiations in the West Nile Region, IDPs, Acholi youth in Uganda, and child soldiers.
    - Zimbabwe
      - Zimbabwe Human Rights Bulletin issues, 2001 and 2003 (Box 19)
        Includes two issues produced by the Zimbabwe Lawyers for Human Rights.
      - Other Publications, 1997-2003
        Topics cover community service, agriculture, the post-presidential election period of March to May 2002, youth militia training; includes a working draft constitution.
  - Asia, 1993-2007, (2.5 boxes)
    - Multi-Country/Regional
      - Interchange. 2003. (Box 19)
        One issue of the publication produced by the Fund for Reconciliation and Development to foster cooperation between Cambodia, Laos, Vietnam, and Cuba.
      - East West Center. After the Tsunami: Human Rights of Vulnerable Populations. Berkeley: Human Rights Center, University of California Berkeley, 2005
      - Dalpino, Catharin and David Steinberg, eds. Georgetown Southeast Asia Survey, 2002-2003. Washington, DC: Georgetown University, 2003
    - Afghanistan, (4 folders)
      Consists of many reports on rule of law, human rights, transitional government, and government reform. Noteworthy authors of the documents are the U.N., the International Crisis Group, the United States Institute of Peace, and the Center for American Progress.
    - Burma
      - Selth, Andrew. Burma's Armed Forces Under Civilian Rule: A Return to the Past? Washington, DC: The Burma Fund, 2001
      - Shan Human Rights Foundation. License to Rape: The Burmese Military Regime's Use of Sexual Violence in the Ongoing War in Shan State. Chiang Mai, Thailand: The Shan Human Rights Foundation, 2002
    - Cambodia
      - Journal Issues, 2000-2006 (Box 20)
        Contains productions from two sources: the Center for Social Development and Searching for the Truth: Magazine of the Documentation Center of Cambodia. Searching for the Truth consists of two individual issues but also two volumes of all issues from 2000 and 2001.
      - Other Publications, 1999-2006
        Contains works discussing corruption, National Assembly sessions, establishing tribunals against Khmer Rouge leaders, and the role of women in post-conflict Cambodia.
    - China
      - Human Rights in China. China Minority Exclusion, Marginalization and Rising Tensions. London: Minority Rights Group International, 2007
    - East Timor
      - Journal issues, 2002-2007
        Work from two sources, the Comissão de Acolhimento, Verdade e Reconciliação de Timor Leste (CAVR) and Estafeta: Voice of the East Timor & Indonesia Action Network.
      - Other publications, 2000-2006
        Includes documents published by the U.N., CAVR, FRIDE, and others about human rights, accountability and justice, and about the establishment of a commission for truth and reconciliation.
    - India
      - Chadda, Maya. Minority Rights and Conflict Prevention: Case Study of Conflicts in Indian Jammu and Kashmir, Punjab and Nagaland. London: Minority Rights Group International, 2006 (Box 21)
      - Habibullah, Wajahat and Zulfiqar Hussain Shah. Human Rights in Jammu and Kashmir. New Delhi: National Human Rights Commission, 2003
    - Indonesia
      - Jakarta Legal Aid Institute. Report on Law and Human Rights 2004: Rain of Impunities for Human Rights Violator. Jakarta: Jakarta Legal Aid Institute, 2004
      - Jakarta. Indonesia in the Circle of Impunity. Jakarta: Commission for Involuntary Disappearances and Victims of Violence
    - Japan
      - United Nations University policy briefs, 2006, (1 folder)
    - Mongolia
      - Global Rights VOICES. Fighting for Survival: Human Rights and Mining in Mongolia. Washington, DC: Global Rights, 2006
    - Philippines
      - Fortunato, Nicolas, ed. Human Rights at the Turn of the 21st Century: 2003 Human Rights Report. Quezon City, Philippines: Task Force Detainees of the Philippines, 2004
      - Parong, Aurora A. and Max M. de Mesa, eds. PGMA's Strong Republic: Building a Culture of Impunity. Quezon City, Philippines: Task Detainees of the Philippines, 2004
      - Quintos-Deles, Teresita. Women, War, and Peacemaking in the Philippines: 1986-1993. Quezon City, Philippines: Gaston Z. Ortigas Peace Institute, 1993
      - Task Force Detainees of the Philippines, et al. A Report on the Phillipine Government's Implementation of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights. Geneva, 2003
    - Russia (including Chechnya)
      - JURIX and the Open Society Justice Initiative. Ethnic Profiling in the Moscow Metro. New York: Open Society Institute, 2006
    - Thailand
      - Biel, Eric, Neil Hicks and Michael McClintock. Losing Ground: Human Rights Defenders and Counterterrorism in Thailand. New York: Human Rights First, 2006
  - Europe, 1994-2006, (2 boxes)
    - Multi-Country/Regional, (2 folders) (Box 21)
      Consists of Centro de Investigacion para la Paz (CIP) reports, a European Union presidential report, work on Europe and Islam as well as work on women's empowerment in Europe.
    - Balkans/Former Yugoslavia
      - Dziedzic, Michael, Laura Rozen and Phil Williams. Lawless Rule versus Rule of Law in the Balkans. Washington, DC: United States Institute of Peace, 2002
      - Schabas, William. Was Genocide Committed in Bosnia and Herzegovina? First Judgments of the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia. Fordham International Law Journal 25.1 (Nov. 2001): 23-53
    - Belarus
      - International Mission of Investigation. Belarus, A Caricature of Autocracy: The Civil Society in a Strangehold. Paris: International Federation for Human Rights, 2001
    - Bosnia and Herzegovina